Guide to the Isaac Backus Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Isaac Backus papers
1660-1806
RG 280
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(20 boxes)
Personal papers of Backus document his professional work and include diaries, travel journals, autobiographical statements, sermons, published and unpublished writings, and extracts from readings. Collected papers include correspondence and narratives chronicling the Separate Baptist struggle for religious freedom, gathered by Backus.
Backus, Isaac, 1724-1806
Biographical / Historical
Isaac Backus was born in Norwich, Connecticut, January 9, 1724. Little is known of his childhood. In "An account of the life of Isaac Backus" (completed to 1756), he provides genealogical information and then begins a detailed chronicle of events leading to his religious conversion and his life after that point.
In response to preaching of the Great Awakening, in 1741 Backus joined the Standing church in Norwich. The Norwich minister was distressed that the converts caused too much agitation and after a few years refused to invite itinerant New Lights, so in 1746 Backus and several other church members withdrew and formed a New Light church. In 1748 Backus became minister of a New Light church in Middleborough, Massachusetts; he continued his association with the New Lights until 1756, when he withdrew because of his opposition to infant baptism. He organized a Separate Baptist church in Middleborough and remained as minister there until his death.
Backus published a large number of tracts and a 3-volume history of the Baptist denomination. His two major concerns are reflected in these works: unification of the Separate Baptists and the struggle against religious taxation as part of efforts to achieve religious freedom. Throughout his professional career Backus travelled extensively in New England, helping to organize churches and settle disputes among various Baptist groups. The Warren Baptist Association was established in 1767; Backus was a member of the Grievance Committee formed to work toward elimination of persecution by civil authorities. As an agent of the Committee he worked to keep the issue of separation of church and state before the general public; and in 1774 he travelled to Philadelphia with other Baptists to seek assistance from the First Continental Congress.
In his later years, Backus continued to be a spokesman for Baptists. He argued for ratification of the U.S. Constitution in 1790, convinced that in effect it stood for separation of church and state by prohibiting any religious test for officeholders. In 1796 he published the third volume of his History, and in 1803 an Abridgement. Backus died in Middleborough, November 20, 1806.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series:
Series I.
Personal Papers
Series II.
Collected Papers
Series III.
Addendum and Fragile Originals
Immediate Source of Acquisition
From the Andover Newton Theological School collection, transferred in 2017
Scope and Contents
The Isaac Backus Papers, 1660-1806, consist of two major components: personal papers and collected papers. The Personal Papers (1746-1806) of Series I document the professional work of Backus and are arranged according to the following categories: diaries, travel journals, autobiographical statements, ordination booklet, sermons, publications, unpublished manuscripts, and extracts from readings. A card index, prepared by Brown University personnel, provides main entry access to the diary. The diary and index are published: William G. McLaughlin, ed., The Diary of Isaac Backus, 3 vols. (Providence: Brown University Press, 1979)
The Collected Papers (1660-1806) of Series II are primarily correspondence and narratives chronicling the Separate Baptist struggle for religious freedom, gathered by Backus. This section also includes all correspondence of Backus and extant records of the Warren Baptist Association. A card index, prepared by Brown University personnel, provides main entry access to the Collected Papers. The index is divided into three general categories: Baptist History, Letters, Warren Association. The following usage notes may be helpful in working with individual indexes: 1) Baptist History --The scope of the index is self-explanatory. IB references include letters of IB to others and IB as the subject of a specific document. 2) Letters -- The index includes letters of others to IB. 3)Warren Association -- The index includes annual letters of individual churches to the association and correspondence dealing with business related to the annual meeting. The index also provides subject access to the unpublished manuscript, "History of the Warren Association."
The third series includes additional documents, fragile originals, and a set of lantern slides related to Backus. These materials are not described in detail in the finding aid that was received with the collection from Andover Newton Theological School. The lantern slides are stored onsite with restricted oversize material due to their fragile nature.
The original PDF finding aid created by Andover Newton Theological School staff, which contains more detailed description of the collection, is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
Baptists -- New England; Baptists -- Clergy; Freedom of religion; Andover Newton Theological School; Backus, Isaac, 1724-1806
- Personal Papers, Series I
  - Diaries
    - volume 2, 1751 July 29–1752 July 25 (Box 1)
    - volume 3, 1752 July 26–1755 April 13 (Box 1)
    - volume 4, 1755 April 20–1759 June 28 (Box 1)
    - volume 6, 1763 July 20–1767 October 11 (Box 1)
    - volume 7, 1767 October 13–1771 October 23 (Box 1)
    - volume 8, 1771 October 25–1775 December 31 (Box 1)
    - volume 9, 1776 January 7–1780 July 27 (Box 1)
    - volume 10, 1780 July 28–1784 December 31 (Box 1)
    - volume 12, 1789 June 21–1796 December 28 (Box 1)
    - volume 13, 1797 January 1–1802 December 31 (Box 1)
    - volume 14, 1803 January 2–1806 March 16 (Box 1)
  - Travel journals
    - List of journeys, 1748–1802 (Box 2)
    - Account of journeys, 1746 September 27–1747 December 3 (Box 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Bound with list of journeys
    - Account of journeys, 1749 November 9–1774 November 19 (Box 2)
  - Autobiographical statements
    - Reasons of separation, Undated (Box 2)
    - Some brief account of my travels and experiences, 1746–1750 (Box 2)
    - A few things concerning marriage, 1748–1749 (Box 2)
    - Some particular account of my conversion, 1751 (Box 2)
    - Some particular account of my settling into ministry in ye joining borders of Bridgewater and Middleborough, 1752 (Box 2)
    - Reasons of my withdrawing communion with Paedobaptists, which I once stood with, 1756 (Box 2)
    - An account of the life of Isaac Backus (completed to January 1, 1756) (Box 2)
    - Day book, 1760–1769 (Box 2)
  - Ordination booklet
    - An account of ordinations, 1746 February–1895 September (Box 2)
  - Sermons
    - Account of texts preacht from, September 13, 1757 - April 6, 1777 (Box 2)
    - Undated sermons (Box 2)
      On the following texts: Genesis 42:36; Job 34:21; Psalm 49:20; Proverbs 13: 10; Ecclesiastes 3:11; Ecclesiastes 7:16; Hosea 13:6; Matthew 28:19-20; Luke 7:9; Romans 10:2; Romans 11: 7; 2 Corinthians 3:3; 2 Corinthians 5:7; Ephesians 6:1; 2 Thessalonians 2:8; 1 Timothy 4:12; 1 Timothy 6:17-19; Hebrews 8: 8-11; James 1:25; James 3: 1; 2 Peter 2:19; Revelation 11: 3 and and two fragments
    - Ezekiel 33:7, 1749 February 23 (Box 2)
    - Hebrews 11:39, 1749 October 29 (Box 2)
      Bound with 23 February 1749
    - Acts 13:36, 1749 November 29 (Box 2)
    - John 9:4, 1750 March 5 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 13:20, 1750 March 17 (Box 2)
    - Hosea 4:17, 1750 March 24 (Box 2)
      Bound with 17 March 1750
    - Matthew 7:26-27, 1751 January 2 (Box 2)
      Bound with undated sermon on 2 Corinthians 5:17
    - 1 John 3:7, 1751 February 4 (Box 2)
    - Ephesians 4:30, 1751 February 17 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 26:20, 1751 September 22 (Box 2)
    - James 1:18, 1755 August 10 (Box 2)
    - Psalm 119:111, 1756 December 26 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 6:6-8, 1757 January 9 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 13:15, 1757 January 23 (Box 2)
    - Job 36:2, 1759 February 25 (Box 2)
    - Ezekiel 1:5, 1761 July 26 (Box 2)
    - Micah 4:11, 1765 February 10 (Box 2)
    - Revelation 2:1, 1765 September 11 (Box 2)
    - Deuteronomy 32:2, 1766 February 23 (Box 2)
    - 1 Peter 1:7, 1766 May 25 (Box 2)
    - Matthew 9:38, 1766 May 25 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 21:16, 1766 June 29 (Box 2)
    - Galatians 5:13, 1766 July 24 (Box 2)
    - Genesis 17:1, 1766 October 19 (Box 2)
    - John 6:32, 1766 October 19 (Box 2)
    - Habakkuk 2:13, 1768 October 2 (Box 2)
    - Romans 5:14, 1768 December 25 (Box 2)
    - 1 Peter 2:11, 1769 January 8 (Box 2)
    - 1 Thessalonians 5:21, 1769 March 3 (Box 2)
    - Acts 17:26-27, 1769 April 16 (Box 2)
    - Romans 7:1, 1769 April 30 (Box 2)
    - 1 John 5:3, 1769 July 30 (Box 2)
    - Genesis 8:21, 1770 January 7 (Box 2)
    - Romans 12:2, 1770 January 30 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 23:14, 1770 February 20 (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 61:2, 1770 February 25 (Box 2)
    - Numbers 11:20, 1770 April 2 (Box 2)
    - Colossians 2:19, 1770 May 3 (Box 2)
    - Hebrews 4:2, 1770 July 8 (Box 2)
    - Galatians 5:16, 1770 August 19 (Box 2)
    - 1 Corinthians, 1770 August 26 (Box 2)
    - 1 Peter 2:24, 1770 September 2 (Box 2)
    - Proverbs 21:2, 1770 November 18 (Box 2)
    - Deuteronomy 18:15, 1771 March 17 (Box 2)
    - Deuteronomy 8:5, 1771 July 23 (Box 2)
    - Matthew 25:8-9, 1771 July 28 (Box 2)
    - Mark 4:26-28, 1771 August 4 (Box 2)
    - Luke 9:23, 1771 August 29 (Box 2)
    - Psalm 27:10, 1771 September 21 (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 26:19, 1771 September 22 (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 29:24, 1771 September 22 (Box 2)
    - Philemon 1:18, 1771 October 2 (Box 2)
    - Psalm 112:7, 1772 January 29 (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 66:2, 1772 February (Box 2)
    - Psalm 125:5, 1772 February 16 (Box 2)
    - Psalm 116:15, 1772 February 23 (Box 2)
    - 2 Peter 3:5, 1772 April 2 (Box 2)
    - Hebrews 13:17, 1772 April 12 (Box 2)
    - Galatians 3:27, 1772 September 6 (Box 2)
    - John 16:33, 1773 April 25 (Box 2)
    - Leviticus 10:3, 1779 March 2 (Box 2)
    - Acts 10:34, 1779 August 8 (Box 2)
    - 2 Kings 4:6, 1779 August 22 (Box 2)
    - Hosea 13:13, 1780 January 16 (Box 2)
    - Esther 4:13, 1780 February 20 (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 44:22, 1800 June 17 (Box 2)
    - Philemon 3:13-14, 1800 June 29 (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - All true ministers of the gospel are called into that work by the special influences of the holy spirit, 1754 (Box 3)
      2 copies
    - An appeal to the public for religious liberty, against the oppressions of the present day, 1773 (Box 3)
    - The atonement of Christ, explained and vindicated against late attempts to exclude it out of the world, 1787 (Box 3)
    - A discourse concerning the materials, the manner of building, and power of organizing of the church of Christ, 1773 (Box 3)
    - The doctrine of sovereign grace opened and vindicated: and also The consistency and duty of declaring divine sovereignty, and mens impotency while yet we address their consciences with the warnings of truth, and calls of the gospel, 1771 (Box 3)
    - A door opened for equal Christian liberty, and no man can shut it, 1783 (Box 3)
    - Evangelical ministers described, and distinguished from legalists, 1772 (Box 3)
    - Family prayer not to be neglected, 1766 (Box 3)
    - A fish caught in his own net. An examination of nine sermons, from Matt. 16.18, published last year, by Mr. Joseph Fish of Stonington, 1768 (Box 3)
      Incomplete manuscript and two copies of published work
    - Gospel comfort for mourners, 1803 (Box 3)
      Second edition; 2 copies
    - Gospel comfort, under heavy tidings, 1769 (Box 3)
    - Government and liberty described, and ecclesiastical tyranny exposed, 1778 (Box 3)
    - A great faith described and inculcated, 1805 (Box 4)
      Manuscript and 3 copies of published work
    - A history of New England; with particular reference to the people called Baptists, Undated (Box 4)
      Proposal for printing by subscription and list of subscribers; fragments of draft of work; draft of index; proposal for volume 2 and manuscript of volume 2 (incomplete); manuscript of Abridgement
    - The infinite importance of the obedience of faith, and of a separation from the world, opened and demonstrated, 1791 (Box 5)
    - A letter to a gentleman in the Massachusetts General Assembly, concerning taxes to support religious worship, 1771 (Box 5)
    - A letter to the Reverend Mr. Benjamin Lord, of Norwich; occasioned by some harsh things which he has lately published against those who have dissented from his sentiments about the ministry, the church, and baptism, 1764 (Box 5)
    - The liberal support of gospel ministers, opened and inculcated, 1790 (Box 5)
      Manuscript and 4 copies of published work
    - A reply to a piece wrote last year, by Mr. Israel Holly, ..., entitled "The New-Testament interpretation of the Old, relative to infant baptism" wherein another short attempt is made toward bringing that controversy to a happy issue, 1772 (Box 5)
    - A seasonable plea for liberty of conscience, against some late oppressive proceedings; particularly in the town of Berwick, in the county of York, 1770 (Box 5)
      Manuscript and copy of published work
    - A short description of the difference between the bond-woman and the free as they are the two covenants, 1770 (Box 5)
    - Spiritual ignorance causeth men to counter-act their doctrinal knowledge, 1763 (Box 5)
    - The substance of an address to an Assembly in Bridgewater, March 10, 1779 previous to the administration of baptism (Box 5)
    - The testimony of the two witnesses, explained and vindicated, with a few remarks upon the late writings of Dr. Hemmenway and Dr. Lathrop, 1793 (Box 5)
    - True faith will produce good works, 1767 (Box 5)
    - Truth is great, and will prevail, 1781 (Box 5)
  - Unpublished manuscripts
    - Fragments (6), Undated (Box 5)
      Some of these unidentified manuscripts might be extracts from Isaac Backus's readings.
    - History of Warren Association to 1785, with sketches of member churches to 1791 (Box 5)
    - The kingdom of God, described by his word, with its infinite benefits to human society (incomplete)
  - Extracts from Isaac Backus's readings
    - Civil records: Connecticut, Undated (Box 5)
    - Civil records: Massachusetts, Undated (Box 6)
    - Civil records: Rhode Island, Undated (Box 6)
    - Civil records: United Colonies, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Connecticut, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Boston/First Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Boston/Second Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Middleborough/First Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Middleborough/Third Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Rehoboth/First Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Rehoboth/Second Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/South Brimfield/Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Swansea/Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Massachusetts/Swansea/Second Baptist Church (in booklet Rehoboth/Second Baptist Church), Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Rhode Island/Newport/First Baptist Church, Undated (Box 6)
    - Church records: Rhode Island/Newport/Second Baptist Church (in' booklet Rehoboth/Second Baptist Church), Undated (Box 6)
    - Authors and various subjects: booklet, Undated (Box 6)
      Includes extracts on the following: baptism; Cotton Mather; [Charles) Rollin's History; Edes & Gill's Gazette (3/1/1773); Boston Gazette (n.d.); [Joseph] Bellamy; Bishop [Benjamin] Hoadley; Boston Evening Post (5/9/1774); [John] Owen; Life of Hanserd Knollys; Ancient records of Plymouth Colony; Experience Mayhew; [Thomas] Prince; [William] Hubbard's Election Sermon; Massachusetts Colony Law Book (1642); A short account of some of the proceedings of the deputies and committee appointed to take care of the civil affairs of dissenters; [Joseph] Phipps, Remarks on the committee's arguments used to support ecclesiastical impositions in our nation; Quakers; [George] Fox and [John] Burnyeat; Stephen Watt, Essay upon moral agency; Cotton Mather, Magnalia
    - Authors and various subjects: booklet, Undated (Box 6)
      Includes extracts on the following: Cotton Mather; Increase Mather; Boston Newsletter (8/27/1761); [John] Gill's Exposition of Revelation; [Isaac] Watt's Logick; Boston Newsletter (4/29/1762); [John H.] Hervey's Letters; Bishop Burnet's translation of History of Persecutions; William Warburton, Sermon preached before the SPG 1766; Massachusetts Gazette (5/28/1767); [Charles] Chauncey, Discourse on the death of Jonathan Mayhew; Hooker, Doubting Christians drawn to Christ; Mayhew, Sermons on striving to be entering at the strait gate; Cotton Mather, Life of John Eliot; Chauncey, Sermon on the validity of Presbyterian ordination; Stoddard, The defects of preachers; Benjamin Church, History of Philip's War; Boston Evening Post (12/26/1768); Ebenezer Frothingham, A key to unlock the door to the religious constitution in Connecticut; Josephus' Antiquities; Benjamin Wallin, Sermon at an ordination in London 1766
    - Individual manuscripts: Morgan Edwards, Materials for a history of Baptists in Rhode Island, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: Governor Winthrop's Journal, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: America Dissected, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: Paul Bunyan, Prison Meditations, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: Roger Williams, The fox digged out of his burrows, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: Spectator, vol.2, #126, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: Letters of Roger Williams and Samuel Hubbard, Undated (Box 6)
    - Individual manuscripts: Diary of John Comer, Undated (Box 6)
- Collected Papers, Series II
  - Usage notes and original finding aid for calendar of Collected Papers (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Copy of calendar of Collected Papers provides information about index entries in card index for Backus collection, which is available in the Special Collections reading room.
  - Fragments and undated papers (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes: fragment: remarks concerning Sarah Thompson statement regarding the Greek word for baptism prayer request of Zulmina Harper and wife; table of contents for Rudiments of North American languages or The young child's grammar.
  - Undated papers (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes:J.C., Remarks against infant baptism; [John ComerJ, List of Baptist churches of London ca.1730; A description of Baptist churches and societies
  - Undated papers (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Includes: [John Davis], History of First Baptist Church of Boston (incomplete); Some things relative to the First Baptist Church in Boston; Spiritual autobiography (unknown hand); Elizabeth Lord, Statement of conversion; Anna Plimpton, Statement of conversion
  - Collected papers in Box 6, 1660–1730 (Box 6)
    View listing of papers in the original finding aid for the collection, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Collected papers in Box 7, 1731–1758 (Box 7)
  - Collected papers in Box 8, 1759–1770 May (Box 8)
  - Collected papers in Box 9, 1770 June–1774 April (Box 9)
  - Collected papers in Box 10, 1774 May–1778 July (Box 10)
  - Collected papers in Box 11, 1778 August–1781 September (Box 11)
  - Collected papers in Box 12, 1781 September–1784 (Box 12)
  - Collected papers in Box 13, 1785–1788 (Box 13)
  - Collected papers in Box 14, 1789–1794 (Box 14)
  - Collected papers in Box 15, 1795–1804 (Box 15)
  - Collected papers in Box 16, 1805–1806 (Box 16)
- Addendum and Fragile Originals, Series III
  - Backus manuscripts copied by Alvah Hovey in conjunction with research for his work A Memoir of the Life and Times of the Rev. Isaac Backus, A.M., 1752–1806 (Box 16)
  - Fragile originals of correspondence, 1715–1784 (Box 16)
    Photocopies of these letters are filed chronologically in the previous boxes.
  - Fragile originals of correspondence, 1786–1804 (Box 17)
  - "Master Photocopies", 1732–1807 (Box 17)
  - Labeled folders of photocopies, including: "History of Warren Association" and "Photocopy of Account of Ordination 1745-1805" (Box 17)
  - Manuscripts of others, including: "IB Memoir" by Alvah Hovery, "Benson's View of Baptism" by Irah Chase, "Ms. Summary of Brown University Theses", miscellaneous unidentified manuscripts (Box 18)
  - Genealogy of the King family of Raynham, MA (1 folder) (Box 18)
  - Documents related to Backus monument (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Photographs (7 folders) (Box 18)
  - Pamphlets: "The Mode and Baptism of Subjects Examined in Seven Sermons" by Daniel Merrill, and "The Port Folio", Vol. V. April, 1811, No. 4. (Box 18)
  - Unidentified notes and "Proposals and Contents of the Baptists Annual Register", 1790 (Box 18)
  - Baptist History chronology (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous non-Backus manuscript letters and documents received with collection (Box 19)
    Note in box indicates that many of the manuscript letters relate to the Massachusetts Baptist Missionary Society.
  - Lantern slides related to Backus (Box 20)
    List of slides in box